{"tossups": [{"question": "One member of this organization, Frankie Yale, was so named because he owned the Harvard Bar and Grill. Precursors of this group included the Dead Rabbits, and a famous member of this group supplied the US Navy with intelligence for (*)  Operation Huskie. This group fought a \"war\" named for a village whose natives attempted to take it over. This group has been regulated in the United States since the 1930s by \"The Commission\", and branches of it include the Unione Corse and the 'Ndrangheta. For ten points, name this loosely-organized American crime group that fought the Castellamarese war, whose members included John Gotti, Charles Luciano, and Alphonse Capone.", "answer": "the  Mafia  (accept \"La Cosa Nostra\")", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>the  Mafia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["the  Mafia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept \"La Cosa Nostra\""}, {"question": "One former president of this country rose to national prominence by founding the yogurt company Tiko. That president founded a party known as \"I love\" this country. One ethnic group in this country, the Antemoro, originated from a group of Meccan settlers in the 15th century. This country's three-tiered social class system was composed of the  (*)Andriana, the Andevo, and the Hova. The predominant pre-colonial kingdom of this country was ruled by a series of queens ending in Ranavalona III. That was the Kingdom of Imerina. For ten points, name this African country originally settled by a Malayo-Polynesian ethnic group.", "answer": "Republic of  Madagascar", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Republic of  <b><u>Madagascar</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Republic of  Madagascar"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "(description acceptable) One attempt to do this was opposed by a guerrilla group who tattooed \"Death to the Chinese\" on each other. Another attempt to do this was defeated at a battle in which iron spikes placed on a riverbed destroyed the attacking fleet. (*)  One attempt to do this involved an attacking army stripping naked before battle to embarrass the defenders. A successful attempt to do this was supposedly done in order to rein in the Black Flag Army. It has nothing to do with Burma, Tibetans, or Uyghurs, but another attempt to do this was one of the Qianlong Emperor's Ten Great Campaigns. That was done in order to suppress the Tay Son Rebellion, and a failed attempt to do this inspired the writing of \"Nam Quoc Song Ho\". For ten points, name this action, attempts at which were foiled by Le Loi and the Trung Sisters.", "answer": "Invading   Vietnam  (accept other things having to do with military actions in 'Nam)", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Invading   Vietnam</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Invading   Vietnam"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept other things having to do with military actions in 'Nam"}, {"question": "During this event, one man was given control of a cavalrysquadron and permission to attack his own lines in order to win a rebel leader's trust. One combatant during this event had a henchman who once shot a man to see which way he would fall ,  and rescheduled (*)  battles and executions to accommodate a film crew. The first ever aerial dogfight occurred during this conflict, during which another combatant arranged the assassination of a rival by his own honor guard. During this conflict, the Ten Tragic Days involved the assassination of Francisco Madero and the collapse of the Aguascalientes Convention. For ten points, name this conflict, in which combatants included Venustiano Carranza, Alvaro Obregon, Emiliano Zapata, and Pancho Villa.", "answer": "Mexican Revolution  (Accept Mexican Civil War)", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Mexican Revolution</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Mexican Revolution"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "Accept Mexican Civil War"}, {"question": "One man probably assassinated in this campaign was nicknamed \"Jango\".One leader participating in this campaign was responsible for a car bomb in Washington that killed Ronni Moffitt as well as its target. A man (*)  involved in this campaign was accused of genocide against the Ache people, and another man involved in this campaign . Another leader involved in this campaign is beloved in right-wing meme circles for throwing Communists out of helicopters and organized the \"Caravan of Death\". For ten points, name this campaign that targeted Joao Goulart and Orlando Letelier as well as torturing Jose Mujica, Michele Bachelet, and Dilma Rousseff.", "answer": "Operation  Condor  (antiprompt on \"Dirty War)", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Operation  Condor</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Operation  Condor"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "antiprompt on \"Dirty War"}, {"question": "The Nor Yungas Road, renowned for its danger, was built by POWs from this country. One leader of this country delayed a shipment from England until he could learn English and read the ship's books, which he did for all incoming ships. That leader (*)  pursued a policy of forced interracial marriage. Eliza Lynch, the mistress of one of his successors, was forced to dig that successor's grave. This nation's Children's Day falls on the anniversary of a battle at which it used child soldiers with painted beards and sticks to fight modern infantry regiments during a war in which they lost the Siege of Humaita. For ten points, name this country that lost 2\u20443 of its male population in the War of the Triple Alliance.", "answer": "Paraguay", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Paraguay</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Paraguay"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One dictator in this country used executioners in Santa suits to kill dissidents in a soccer stadium while blasting the song \"Those Were the Days\", and another joined La Francophonie after feeling snubbed by his nation's former colonial power. This country (*)  was marred by intercommunal violence between the Bubi and the Fang. This country's founder compelled his people to refer to him as \"Papa\" and added his name to prayers in this country's Catholic churches. He was deposed in a coup by his nephew, the current president. This country was known as Rio Muni under colonial rule, and its capital is located on the island of Fernando Po. For ten points, name this country, which is not actually located on its namesake geographical feature.", "answer": "Equatorial Guinea", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Equatorial <b><u>Guinea</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Equatorial Guinea"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "An Australian expedition to this place was recalled after the death of Belgrave Ninnis. The \"Little America\" base was located here, and another expedition to this region used the  Fram, the former ship of the creator of a passport for stateless peoples. This location (*)  was first sighted by Fabian von Bellingshausen, and Troll Station is located here. Another expedition to this location was marooned on Elephant Island before being relieved by the  Yelcho. Yet another expedition inadvisably used tractors and horses for transport. Queen Maud Land and Terre Adelie are areas of this location, which contains research stations such as Dome Fuji and Zhongshan. For ten points, name this continent that contains \"stations\" named after Douglas Mawson, Robert Scott, and Roald Amundsen.", "answer": " Antarctica  (anti-prompt on \"South Pole\" before \"continent\")", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Antarctica</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Antarctica"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "anti-prompt on \"South Pole\" before \"continent\""}, {"question": "A Napoleonic-era army regiment from Brunswick that fought at Quatre Bras was often known by this color. Count Fulk III of Anjou, nicknamed after this color, was known for murdering his enemies and being the ancestor of the House of Plantagenet. One faction named (*)  for this color advocated imperial expansion of Florence and expelled Dante Alighieri for opposing them. \"Ich dien\" was the motto of one prince known by this color. That prince won the battle of Najera while campaigning to restore Pedro the Cruel to the Castilian throne, as well as the battles of Poitiers and Crecy. For ten points, name this color, by which Edward of Woodstock is often known.", "answer": "Black", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Black</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Black"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One man who claimed to invent this object derived inspiration for it by looking at a potato field in Idaho. That man's progress was delayed when his laboratory burned down twice. Another man (*)  who claimed to have invented this device said of it: \"I never let my children near the thing\". A doll's head was used in the first demonstration of this device, and Johann Hittorf used a Crookes Tube to discover a type of radiation key to the functioning of this device. A process called \"degaussing\" had to be used on early versions of this device. For ten points, name this device that originally used a Cathode Ray Tube to send visual signals.", "answer": "television", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>television</u></b>", "acceptable": ["television"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One leader of this modern-day country was mired in scandal when his army chief attempted to deposit a gold bar at a local bank branch. One king in this modern-day country, who was exiled after taking the presidency, was nicknamed \"King Freddy\". The traditional kings of this country are titled  kabakas (*) , and the aforementioned leader was overthrown in a coup by General Bazilio Okello. One leader in this country called his secret police the \"State Research Bureau\" and caused an international outcry when he killed Archbishop Janani Luwum. The current president of this country was once the leader of the National Resistance Army. For ten points, name this country where the Luwero Triangle was the site of abuses by Apollo Milton Obote and the Raid on Entebbe occurred.", "answer": "Uganda", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Uganda</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Uganda"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This island was the site of a native rebellion over suspicion of poisoned wine that resulted in the execution of 37 conspirators. This island was also the site of Koshamain's Rebellion and Shakushain's Rebellion. A (*)  city on this island hosted the 1972 Winter Olympics. This island was declared a republic with the assistance of Jules Brunet in 1869. A strait separating this island from another was the site of a battle in which the  Petropavlovsk was sunk, and it is separated by the La Perouse Strait from a territory once known as Karafuto. i For ten points, name this island, site of several Ainu Rebellions and the city of Sapporo, as well as the basis for the Pokemon region of Sinnoh..", "answer": "Hokkaido", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Hokkaido</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Hokkaido"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One treaty was signed in this city by Pierre Louis Napoleon Cavagnari, who later became its British Resident. This was the location of the executions of William MacNaghten and Muhammad (*)  Najibullah. One journey originating   in this city was only survived by William Brydon and commanded by William Elphinstone. One campaign whose target was this city was commanded by Frederick \"Bobs\" Roberts. This city became the capital of an empire that won the Third Battle of Panipat, and Operation Storm-333 captured several key objectives in this city and successfully overthrew Hafizullah Amin. For ten points, name this city, the capital of a nation invaded by Britain, Russia, and the United States.", "answer": "Kabul", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Kabul</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Kabul"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This civilization was the first to use dentures, and D.H. Lawrence wrote a travelogue titled after this civilization. This civilization's supreme goddess was Uni, and this civilization's language is responsible for a set of sound shifts in Greek loanwords. (*)  Emperor Claudius wrote a multi-volume history of this civilization after his marriage to a princess from this civilization. One person from this civilization is the villain of a Shakespearean narrative poem,  The Rape of Lucrece. For ten points, name this pre-Roman civilization that founded the cities of Veii and Caisra, as well as one named after its ruling house, Tarquinii.", "answer": "Etruscan", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Etruscan</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Etruscan"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One duke of this region built a prank palace that contained, among other things, trap doors that would dump soot and flour on people entering rooms. One ruler from this region murdered the Duke of Orleans, and (*)  this region was divided into \"Upper\", \"Middle\", and \"Lower\" administrative circles in the Holy Roman Empire. One duke of this region's nickname can be translated as \"rash\", but he is normally spoken of in historical records as \"Charles the Bold\". An army from this region was responsible for capturing Joan of Arc. For ten points, name this region known for its distinctively-hued wine once led by Philip the Good and John the Fearless.", "answer": "Burgundy  (accept  Bourgogne )", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Burgundy</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Burgundy"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept  Bourgogne"}, {"question": "One mayor of this city inspired controversy when a camera caught him uttering profanities and anti-Semitic slurs, after which he offered the unconvincing explanation that he was calling the speaker a \"faker\". Another mayor of this city was assassinated by Patrick Prendergast. Another mayor (*)  was killed by Giuseppe Zangara in an attempt to assassinate the President. The first man mentioned had his namesake Delegation unseated at a national convention of his party, and the latter two were Carter Harrison and Anton Cermak. This city was the namesake of a group of seven protestors arrested during an event here in which police used \"Gestapo tactics\". For ten points, name this city, the home of the 1968 Democratic National Convention in which Barack Obama worked as a community organizer.", "answer": "Chicago", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Chicago</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Chicago"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One Prime Minister of this country was repeatedly run over by trucks after he attempted to flee it by crossdressing. This country was united in the 1950s with a neighboring nation it shared a dynasty with, and this country's  (*) Party of National Brotherhood attempted to align it with the Axis Powers. One autonomous region in this country was the location of a civil war between two rival political dynasties, one of which rules that region today. One leader of this country promised to fight \"the mother of all battles\" before being defeated in a war fought over \"horizontal drilling\". For ten points, name this country whose Talabani and Barzani families fought the Kurdish Civil War and Saddam Hussein overthrew Abdul Karim Qasim.", "answer": "Iraq", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Iraq</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Iraq"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One ruler with this characteristic rode his horse into the sea after being attacked by the Kingdom of Aksum prior to the Year of the Elephant. A large archive related to these people was stored in the Cairo Genizah. One tribe (*) with this characteristic was massacred after their defeat at the Battle of the Trench. That tribe was the Banu Qurayza. One group with this characteristic lives on the Tunisian island of Djerba, and the seat in the Iranian parliament reserved for these people is currently held by Siamak Moreh Sedgh. One non-Mongol horde with this characteristic maintained a namesake \"Pax\" among neighboring steppe peoples. People with this characteristic met with the Jesuit missionary Matteo Ricci upon his arrival in Kaifeng. For ten points, name this characteristic shared by Joseph Dhu-Nuwas and Khans Aaron and Benjamin of Khazaria.", "answer": "  Jew ishness (or Judaism) (or less awkwardly-phrased things relating to Jews)", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Jew ishness</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Jew ishness"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Judaism"}, {"question": "Sultan Suleiman Du ruled the Kingdom of the Pacified thisdirection, and the Taiping under-king associated with this direction recruited the Zhuang to the Taiping cause. He was Feng Yunshan. This (*)  direction names the Brazilian state that is home to the city of Porto Alegre, and this direction is the only cardinal direction not to have a branch of the Xiongnu named after it. The adjectival form of this direction was once part of the name of a country led at various times by Godfrey Huggins and Ian Smith. Name this cardinal direction that Shreve protests to Quentin Compsonthat he does not hate in Faulkner's  Absalom, Absalom.", "answer": "South", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>South</u></b>", "acceptable": ["South"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man's mother encouraged him to become \"Lord of theUmbrellas\", and one group named after this man was founded by a political cartoonist, Bal Thackeray. This man escaped a meeting with a neighboring sultan by hiding in a basket of pastries (*) , and this man was crowned at Raigad Fort, thus founding a kingdom named for his ethnic group. A 190-meter statue of this man is under construction 4 kilometers off the coast of a city whose international airport is named for him. This man killed one of his enemies, Afzal Khan, by disemboweling him with hidden steel tiger claws. For ten points, name this founder of the Maratha Kingdom whose son was executed by his perennial enemy, Aurangzeb.", "answer": "Shivaji", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Shivaji</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Shivaji"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One individual involved in this event bragged about his Medal of Honor when running for office in 1965. Radyo Veris aired the message of one individual involved in this event. A First Quarter Storm preceded this event and prompted the martial law that figured prominently in this event. This event started after Defense Minister Juan Ponce Enrile and Armed Forces Vice-Chief of Staff Fidel V. Ramos, who were both members of the Rolex 12, withdrew (*)  from the government. Jaime Cardinal Sin backed this event by utilizing the power of the Catholic Church. An election preceding this event saw claims of fraud which prompted protests at Malacan\u0303ang Palace.The leader primarily affected by this event had assassinated principal political rival and American exile Ninoy Aquino. For 10 points, identify this event that ousted dictator Ferdinand Marcos from the Philippines.", "answer": "People Power Revolution", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>People Power Revolution</u></b>", "acceptable": ["People Power Revolution"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}